[Music]
sleep is crucial to the development of
physically and psychologically healthy
children but a number of factors have
been identified as interfering with
sufficient sleep including the use of
electronic media devices these days most
children and nearly all adolescents have
at least one such device in their sleep
environment with most used near bedtime
and such use is associated with
inadequate sleep quantity and quality
with resultant excessive daytime
sleepiness so there are calls to
minimize device access at bedtime but
wait a second not so fast i mean which
came first the media use or the sleeping
problem are they not sleeping because
they're on their phone or are they on
their phone because they can't sleep
higher media use has been consistently
associated with all sorts of sleeping
problems
is it because they're so caught up they
push back their bedtimes or does it so
kind of key them up that they have
trouble falling asleep
in college-age students it may be more
of the reverse than not sleeping leading
to pulling out their screens instead of
just staring at the ceiling though in
early childhood it may be a bit of both
how might screen time interfere with
sleep
may not just be pushing back bedtimes
and over stimulation the light
emitted from devices may affect
circadian timing by interfering with the
production of melatonin the sleepiness
hormone that starts ramping up as soon
as the sun goes down but put a screen in
someone's face the excess light at night
may confuse your brain
uh look of course if you're sitting
there checking email with the lights on
then you're already overexposed and a
little extra from the screen may not
make much of a difference but if you're
sitting in the dark
and you know need to send off that final
text or something then having the light
settings tweaked to yellow your screen
may help
but what about the cell phone radiation
might leaving your phone on the
nightstand somehow affect your sleep
there's an enzyme called the beta trace
protein that makes a sleep promoting
neural hormone in the brain and
researchers found that those with
greater long-term cell or cordless phone
exposure tend to have lower levels of
this enzyme in their bloodstream so the
thinking is that the emissions may
affect the release from the tissue
surrounding the brain especially those
right up under the skull closest to the
phone
so
there is a kind of possible mechanism if
cell phones do indeed affect sleep but
you simply don't know
until you put it to the test
study participants were exposed to 30
minutes of a cell phone in talk listen
standby or off modes all the lights and
speakers were disabled there was
insulation used to prevent them from
feeling if it was heating up or anything
so the participants didn't know which
group they were in
after the exposure they took the phones
away shut off the lights and told them
to try to fall asleep
those exposed to the phone when it was
off or in listen or standby mode fell
asleep within 20-30 minutes
but after being exposed to the same
phone in talk mode
it took an average of closer to 50
minutes to fall asleep
the reason for the significant
difference between talking and listening
might be due to the fact that the
typical sar value the specific
absorption rate how much cell phone
energy your body absorbs is about nine
times higher when you're talking than
when you're just listening to someone
else talk
when you do finally get to sleep though
what are the effects of cell phone
exposure on sleep quality there's been
about 20 studies
i split about half and half in terms of
whether cell phone exposure affected
sleep parameters and not all in a
negative way it reminds me of the brain
function data yeah an increase in the
excitability in the brain cortex the
outer layer of the brain in response to
exposure to cell phone emissions might
disrupt sleep
but that increased excitability may mean
like faster reaction times
similarly in affected study subjects
those exposed to an active cell phone
showed significantly more are sleep
but r stands for rem so they got like
four percent more potential dream time
so that's not necessarily a bad thing
[Music]
you